Gilbert T. Smith Collection Relating to Rev. James Dempster
Gilbert T. Smith Collection Relating to Rev. James Dempster
1776-1958
Smith, Gilbert T.
0.25 linear ft.
Research files compiled by Gilbert T. Smith, relating to Methodist minister James Dempster. All modern photocopies, no original material.
4854636
Biographical History
James Dempster (1740-1804) was a Methodist clergyman. Born in Scotland, he studied at Edinburgh University. He and several other lay preachers were sent to America around 1774 by John Wesley. Dempster settled in the Mohawk Valley area of New York, from which base he traveled upstate New York as an itinerant preacher and minister.
The material in the collection was compiled by Gilbert T. Smith.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Gilbert T. Smith Collection Relating to Rev. James Dempster consists of various material -- church records, essays, recollections, etc. -- relating to Methodist clergyman James Dempster. All items are modern photocopies; the collection contains no original material.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is in alphabetical order by title or topic.
Subject and Genre Headings
Biography; Religion and philosophy; Church and clergy; New York State; Dempster, James, 1740-1804.; Smith, Gilbert T.; Methodist Church -- Clergy.; Clergy -- United States.; Methodists -- New York (State); Methodists -- United States.; Bibliographies.; Church records.; Essays.; Research notes.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gilbert Smith, 2007.
Inventory
- Research files
  - Baptism and marriage records as recorded by Rev. James Dempster, 1778-1803 (Box 1)
  - A calm address to our American colonies / Wesley, 1776 (Box 1)
  - The Dempster records / Hartley, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Early American Methodism [excerpt] / Barclay, 1949; excerpt only (Box 1)
  - Encyclopedia of World Methodism [excerpt] / Harmon, 1974; article on Dempster (Box 1)
  - A flame of fire / Schwartz, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Journals and letters of Francis Asbury, Volume I [excerpt] / Clark, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of the annual conferences of the Methodist Episcopal Church, for the years 1773-1828, Volume I [excerpt], 1840 (Box 1)
  - Reclaiming of James Dempster / Schwartz, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Recollections of John Dempster / McKean (Box 1)
  - Records of the United Presbyterian Church in the town of Florida, Montgomery County, N.Y. [excerpt] / Vosburgh (Ed.), 1919 (Box 1)
  - Selected sources of information about Rev. James Dempster / Smith, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Story of the Rev. James Dempster / Kroeger, 1938 (Box 1)